<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Doctor Wallis's letter touching the doctrine of the blessed Trinity answer'd by his friend.</title>
            <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70687</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1506A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R211864</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12637956</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12637956</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64947</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70687)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64947)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1750:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Doctor Wallis's letter touching the doctrine of the blessed Trinity answer'd by his friend.</title>
                  <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Written in response to John Wallis' "Doctrine of the blessed Trinity."</note>
                  <note>Written by Stephen Nye. Cf. Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>This item also appears at reel 344:13 as part of: The faith of one God. London, 1691 (Wing F258B).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wallis, John, 1616-1703. --  Doctrine of the blessed Trinity.</term>
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:64947:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64947:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Doctor Wallis's</hi> LETTER Touching the DOCTRINE OF THE Bleſſed Trinity Anſwer'd by his FRIEND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Read your Letter touching the Doctrine of the Bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, you were pleas'd to ſend me, with a great deal of At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and Satisfaction; and thereupon went to viſit a Neighbour of mine, one that is reputed a modeſt Gentleman, but one that is alſo repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian</hi> or <hi>Socinian.</hi> I ſhew'd him your Letter, and made no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but it would Convince him, as it had done me, that they who denied the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, Three diſtinct Perſons to be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64947:2"/>each of them God in the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Senſe of that Term, and yet but One God, were in a very dangerous and palpable Errour. But I found my ſelf greatly miſtaken; for be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently told me, that you had unfairly repreſented them, charging them with an Opinion which they abhor, to wit, That <hi>how clear ſoever the Expreſſions of Scripture be, or can be, to</hi> this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>they will not believe it, as being inconſistent with Natural Reaſon. And therefore though they do not think fit to give us a bare-fac'd Rejection of Scripture, yet they do (and muſt they tell us) put ſuch a forc'd Senſe on the words of it (be they never ſo plain) as to make them ſignifie ſomewhat elſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He told me he did very much wonder, and was ſorry for your ſake, that a Man of ſuch Reputation for Learning and Piety, ſhould be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſo much uncharitable raſhneſs againſt a Party of Men, which even ſome of their Adverſaries being Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, are both Learned and Pious, though Erroneous. If it were not their hearty Zeal for one of the great and clear Attributes of God! (the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus) his U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; What (ſaith he to me, with a moſt compaſſionate Concern) ſhould make them expoſe themſelves to all manner of Obloquy, Reproach, and Deteſtation of almoſt all that go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Name of Chriſtians, in theſe Parts, to the utmoſt of Injuries and Perfections, the loſs of their Imployments, Eſtates, Liberties, Countries, and ſome of them of Life it ſelf, by the violent Death of Hereticks? Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they this from an Enthuſiaſtic Heat, nor yet upon the account of ſome indifferent, or next to indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things in the Worſhip and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church; it's no leſs than the Incommunicable Nature of the <hi>only Potentate,</hi> King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, that they ſuffer for; hoping for their Reward through the Faith of thoſe Promiſes revealed by Chriſt our Lord, and recorded only in the Holy Scriptures. The Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity whereof none have maintained with ſtronger Reaſonings, nor are more diligent in ſearching out the true Senſe of them, nor are more ready to ſubmit to their Dictates. He ſaid moreover, That it was too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, for even Learned Men to charge die <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> under the Name of <hi>Socinians,</hi> with ſuch Sayings as their Adverſaries charge them with by Conſequences, without reading their Books. Nay, it is well known at <hi>Oxford,</hi> that one in an Act there, diſputing for his Degree in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, took a <hi>Theſis</hi> to maintain, to the very ſame purpoſe with that which your Friend avers againſt the <hi>Socinians,</hi> but his Learned Opponent having read their Books, did ſo baffle him, that it appeared the Reſpondent had not read them; but took his Teſtimonies from their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. I would fain think otherwiſe of Dr. <hi>Wallis;</hi> but he gives me here too much cauſe to ſuſpect him; I will appeal to you (ſaith he) whether he does not.</p>
            <p>Then he fetch'd me <hi>Socinus de Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate S. Script.</hi> and read in pag. 16. <hi>Quod enim ad Rationes attinet, haec nimis fallax via eſt in re quae ex Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina patefaction pendeat, qualis eſt Chriſtiana Religion.</hi> 
               <q>For as to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, this is too fallible a way in a Matter which depends on Divine Revelations, ſuch as Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is.</q> Next he brought <hi>Sclichtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> another eminent Writer that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64947:2"/>followed <hi>Socinus;</hi> He in his Book <hi>Adv. Meifn. de SS. Trin. p.</hi> 68. His Adverſary had ſaid, That Holy Scripture only is the moſt perfect Rule of Faith and Life. To which <hi>Sclichtingius</hi> anſwers <q>That if <hi>de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, clariſſimis verbis in Scriptura conſignatis,</hi> &amp;c. it be touching Points expreſt in Scripture in moſt clear words, ſo that no Man of a ſound Mind can doubt of the Senſe of them, then he grants it; and that chiefly, becauſe it is moſt certain, That <hi>the Scripture contains nothing that is repugnant to manifeſt Reaſon,</hi> or that implies a real Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But if it treat of obſcure Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, every one ſees that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be determin'd without Reaſon, which yet is not to be ſetch'd in, as if it could be oppoſed to Scripture, affirming or denying any thing, but only to declare, whether ſuch a thing be contained in Scripture, or not? If it appear to be contain'd in it, whatſoever Reaſon may ſtill ſay in Contradiction, it muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be deceived.</q> This, ſays my Gentleman, is a clear Account of the <hi>Socinians</hi> Judgment in this Point, and is a direct Confutation of what you have read me out of your Doctor's Letter. He added yet another of their great Men, <hi>Smalcius contr. Frant. Diſp.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 137. <q>
                  <hi>Nulla enim eſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianae Religionis particular,</hi> &amp;c. There is not the leaſt part of Chriſtian Religion, which doth not accord with Reaſon, and that Opinion, which doth not agree with Reaſon, can have no place in Divinity. As a ſmall Light to a great one, ſo Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is not contrary to Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Let <hi>Frantzius,</hi> or any body elſe, tells us of any one Sentence of Holy Scripture that is repugnant to Reaſon, and then let Reaſon be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in the Church. Religion and Holy Scripture hath many things above Reaſon, and therein it highly commends it ſelf, but nothing which is contrary to Reaſon.</q> Of theſe two laſt Paſſages the learned and candid Dr. <hi>Tenniſon</hi> takes notice (in his Book <hi>The Difference betwixt the Proteſtant and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian Methods</hi>) in Abatement of his Charge againſt ſome <hi>Socinians</hi> for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting Reaſon too much. <hi>Perhaps</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>your Friend, Dr.</hi> Wallis, <hi>had read that Book, but took no notice of the Quotations in the Margin.</hi> And if he were put to't, to maintain his Charge, <hi>viz. That they do (and muſt, they tell us) put ſuch a farced Senſe on the words of it [the Scripture] (be they never ſo plain) as to make them ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy ſomewhat elſe:</hi> I am perſwaded he would acquit himſelf no better than the Candidate in Divinity I told you of.</p>
            <p>He was much concerned at the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſneſs of this Imputation; and ſaid, He thought there was no ſort of Proteſtants, of different Sentiments from the Publick, that were ſo inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly dealt with as the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians;</hi> for they are ſo far from denying there are Three Perſons in One God, and aſſerting only One, in oppoſition to the plaineſt Scriptures, that they are thorowly perſwaded, the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherever it is plain, is on their ſide. For does not every Text in the whole Bible, that ſpeaks clearly of the moſt High God, ſpeak of him as One ſingle Perſon, except only two or three obſcure Paſſages in <hi>Geneſis?</hi> Neither can we have any Idea or Conception of God, but <hi>Perſon</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in it, taking Perſon for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Being; ſo that all plain and clear Scriptures militate for them;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64947:3"/>and the <hi>Trinitarians,</hi> or thoſe that ſay there are Three Perſons in God, or that <hi>Three Perſons are all one God,</hi> as your Doctor ſays, have no Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures left, but thoſe that are obſcure. And that they are obſcure, appears clearly by this; That there is ſcarce one Text alledged, by them, which is not otherwiſe expounded, and in conſiſtency with the Unity of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God by their Writers. You may ſee a great number of theſe Texts and Expoſitions, in a Book entituled, <hi>Scriptura S. Trin. Revelatrix, under the Name of</hi> Cingallus.</p>
            <p>Your Doctor (proceeds he) names but two Texts, for he rakes his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for granted, as ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by others. His firſt Text is, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>There are Three that bear Witneſs in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt, and theſe Three are One.</hi> One would expect now that the Learned Doctor, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming but two Texts, ſhould cull out thoſe that were ſtrongeſt for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and yet this Text is ſo far from being clear and ſtrong, That, 1. it has not the Authority as other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures have; for it appears not in the moſt ancient Copies of the <hi>Greek,</hi> nor in the <hi>Syriack,</hi> nor <hi>Arabick,</hi> nor <hi>Ethiopick,</hi> nor <hi>Armenian Bibles,</hi> nor in the moſt eminent <hi>Latin Bibles.</hi> 'Tis not urged by the Fathers in their Diſputes about this Queſtion. It's wholly rejected by ſome, and counted doubtful by almoſt all Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Men. You may ſee (ſaith he) in Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Letter in his Travels, how va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly and uncertainly that Text ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in Ancient Manuſcripts. Here my Neighbour crav'd my Pardon, went to his Cloſet, and preſently brought me a Greek Teſtament, printed at <hi>Strasburg</hi> by <hi>Wolfius Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalaeus, Anno</hi> 1524. in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Reformation, wherein this Verſe is wanting. Bur, <hi>2ly,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing it to be Authentick, yet the moſt Learned, even of the <hi>Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> underſtand it not thus, <hi>Theſe Three are One God,</hi> but <hi>Theſe Three are One in Teſtimony,</hi> or agree in Teſtimony. See <hi>Beza, Vatablus, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, Eraſmus,</hi> the Engliſh <hi>Geneva</hi> Notes. As for his other Text, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. I refer you to <hi>The Brief Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in four Letters,</hi> whereof he gave me a Copy. Only I deſire you (ſays he) to conſider how clear a Proof this Text is, which muſt run thus: <hi>We are Baptized in</hi> [or <hi>into</hi>] <hi>the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt; Therefore theſe Three Perſons are One God, and each of them by himſelf God.</hi> As if the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> by being Baptized into <hi>Moſes,</hi> and believing in the Lord, and in <hi>Moſes</hi> his Servant, (ſo Marg. <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.31.) did acknowledg <hi>Moſes</hi> to be a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the moſt high God, though he was indeed, in ſome ſenſe, a <hi>God</hi> to them; for he was ſo to <hi>Aaron</hi> their High Prieſt: for thus it is read in the Margin of the Engliſh Bible, printed in 1660. <hi>He ſhall be to thee a Mouth, and thou ſhalt be to him a God,</hi> Exod. 4.16. You may ſee the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> ſo render'd, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. and the <hi>Greek,</hi> Heb. 8.10.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs to you, Sir, I could not tell what to oppoſe to this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his, which ſhew'd the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity of our Texts; and he now made a Pauſe, and expected my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: Wherefore to divert him from taking notice of my Convictions, I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him if he had any other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove that Obſcurity? He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64947:3"/>Yes: And that alſo is taken (ſaith he) from our Adverſaries the <hi>Trinitarians,</hi> I mean, the <hi>Romaniſts:</hi> For they are told by Mr. <hi>Chilling-worth,</hi> (the Glory of Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants) and ſince that by Dr. <hi>Tenni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> in his words, thus: <q>For Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, your Men deny very plainly and frequently, that this Doctrine of the Trinity, can be proved by it. See, if you pleaſe, this plainly taught, and urged very earneſtly by Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Hoſius de Author. S. Script. l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 53. by <hi>Gordonius Huntlaeus contr. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Controv.</hi> 1. <hi>de Verbo Dei, c.</hi> 19. by <hi>Gretſerus</hi> and <hi>Tannerus</hi> in <hi>Colloquio Ratisbon;</hi> and alſo by <hi>Vega, Poſſevin, Wiekus,</hi> and others.</q> Now it is to be obſerved, That theſe Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Men, eſpecially <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and <hi>Wiekus</hi> after him, have urged all the Scriptures they could, with their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt induſtry, find out in this Cauſe, and yet, after all, they acknowledg their Inſufficiency and Obſcurity; whereby they give a clear Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the Doctrine of God's being One Perſon; which to deny, were even to deny the whole Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>But beſides the current of all Scriptures on our ſide, we have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny clear Texts that prove the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only to be God. I'll name but two: Our Lord himſelf profeſſes in his ſolemn Prayer to his Father, in the preſence of his Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>This is Eternal Life, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent,</hi> John 17.3. And the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to Gods many, and Lords many, <hi>But to us there is but One God, the Father, of whom are all things, and we in him; and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom are all things, and we by him,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.6. Can any words be more expreſs to prove that there is but One true God, and One Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that One God, to wit, the Father of our lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is oppos'd to him by his Names, Relations, and Characters? Again, there be a multitude of Texts that deny thoſe things of Chriſt, which cannot be denied of God; and that affirm ſuch things of him that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree to him, if he were a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God. In like manner of the Holy Ghoſt. Which of both ſorts you may find urg'd and defended in the two Books of <hi>John Crellius,</hi> touching One God the Father; and abridg'd in <hi>Wolzogenius</hi>'s <hi>Praeparatio ad utilem Lectionem Lib. N. T. cap.</hi> 2, 3, 4, 5. So alſo in your <hi>Brief Hiſtory, &amp;c.</hi> the firſt Letter.</p>
            <p>I then deſired to know of the Gentleman, what he could ſay to the Tradition of the Chriſtian Church; for you ſay, that That <hi>from the Time of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles hitherto, as well before as ſince, the Council of</hi> Nice <hi>hath ever held the Divinity of theſe three Perſons, and that theſe three are but One God.</hi> This alſo you take for granted. He anſwered, 1. It is the Catholick Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of all Proteſtants, that the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures are a compleat Rule of Faith and Manners, and clear and plain in all things neceſſary. Now ſince this Doctrine of the Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in One God, is held a Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental and Neceſſary Doctrine, it muſt conſequently be clear and plain to all honeſt Enquirers, which I clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee it is not, therefore I can ſatisfy my ſelf concerning it, without an end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Enquiry into the Fathers and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I am ſure it has not been held
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64947:4"/>in the Apoſtles Time, nor, I believe, in any of the Three firſt Centuries, nor even in the Three next, without much oppoſition.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I think that <hi>Curcellaeus</hi> has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as well as any thing can be proved out of Ancient Writings, That the Doctrine of the Trinity, about the Time of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> was of a ſpecial Union of Three Perſons in the Deity, and not of a numerical, as it is now taught, and has been taught ſince the Chimerical Schoolmen were hearkned unto.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I wonder how Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons the Chriſtian Church, ſince he knows there were divers <hi>Arian</hi> Councils, and one of them, that of <hi>Ariminum,</hi> conſiſted of 550 Biſhops, the moſt numerous Aſſembly of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops perhaps as ever was; except he accounts <hi>A ians</hi> for <hi>Trinitarians;</hi> which if he do, then he cannot chuſe but reckon Mr. <hi>Biddle</hi> for one too; for he Titles his Book, <hi>The Apoſtolical and True Opinion concerning the Holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity revived and aſſerted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. According to what I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven my ſelf leave to read in the Controvertiſts of theſe Times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that Matter, I mean <hi>Curcellae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>Mareſius, Sandius,</hi> and <hi>Gardner,</hi> and <hi>Bull, Petavius, Biddle, Eſtwich,</hi> and <hi>Le Clerk;</hi> I reckon <hi>Curcellaeus, Bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,</hi> and <hi>Le Clerk</hi> to be the more free and ingenuous Writers, and therefore more likely to give a true Judgment concerning the Matters they enquire of.</p>
            <p>But, 6. I conclude my Judgment with that of the great Proteſtant Champion <hi>Chillingworth, chap.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 56. — <q>By the Religion of Proteſtants, I do not underſtand the Doctrine of <hi>Luther,</hi> or <hi>Calvin,</hi> or <hi>Melancthon;</hi> nor the Confeſſion of <hi>Auguſta,</hi> or <hi>Geneva,</hi> nor the Catechiſm of <hi>Heidel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> nor the Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> no, nor the Harmony of Proteſtant Confeſſions; but that wherein they all agree, and which they all Subſcribe with a greater Harmony, as a perfect Rule of their Faith and Actions, that is, the BI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE, the BIBLE, the BIBLE only is the Religion of Proteſtants! whatſoever elſe they believe, beſides it, and the plain, irrefragable, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitable Conſequences of it, well may they hold it as a Matter of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, but as Matter of Faith and Religion; neither can they, with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence to their own Grounds, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it themſelves, nor require the Belief of it of others, without moſt high and moſt ſchiſmatical Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I (for my part) after a long, and as I verily believe and hope, impartial ſearch of the true Way to Eternal Happineſs, do profeſs plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that I cannot find any reſt for the ſole of my Foot, but upon this Rock only. I ſee plainly, and with mine own Eyes, that there are Popes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Popes, Councils againſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, ſome Fathers againſt others, the ſame Fathers againſt themſelves; a Conſent of Fathers of one Age, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Conſent of Fathers of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Age; the Church of one Age, againſt the Church of another Age. — No Tradition, but only of Scripture, can derive it ſelf from the Fountain — In a word, there is no ſufficient certainty but of Scripture only, for any conſidering Man to build upon.</q> I would not have Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> think to impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us in this Reign of a Proteſtant King and Queen, the Doctrine of Tradition; he had better have done it in the late King's Time, then it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64947:4"/>would have been acceptable to the Court.</p>
            <p>Sir, I hope (proceeded my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour) you are by this time convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced how unjuſtly and unlike a Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar the Doctor (pardon, I pray, my Reſentment) has drawn ſo black an Indictment againſt the <hi>Socinians,</hi> upon falſe Grounds, taken for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him to be true. I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to read his words: <hi>Nor do the Anti-Trinitarians inſist on any other Ground, why they deny it,</hi> [the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Three Perſons of One God] <hi>ſave only, That it ſeems to them ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely impoſſible; and therefore think themſelves bound to put another ſenſe on all places of Scripture (how clear ſoever they be, or can be) which prove or favour it.</hi> It's the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of that Doctrine to a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand clear places of Scripture, which they inſiſt upon, as I have ſhew'd before: But I will purſue it a little further. Will the Doctor deny that the Perſon of the Father is God? No, his Opinion aſſerts it. Will he then deny, That he who is God, is not All-ſufficient or Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? If that One Perſon be All-ſufficient, (and he is not God if he be not) then all other Perſons, beſides him, muſt of neceſſity be ſuperfluous, and the introducing them into the Godhead is plain Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytheiſm, and a direct Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the firſt Commandment of the Decalogue, and to all thoſe Texts that aſſert God to be One, and conſequently to thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that ſpeak of God as One Perſon, which are without number. No, they firſt devis'd an Opinion, which is contrary to the cleareſt Scriptures, and the moſt evident Reaſons, and then they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us it is a Myſtery, either which we cannot underſtand, and therefore muſt be blind to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions that are in it; or, if we will not be ſo ſatisfied, they call us <hi>Clamorous</hi> and <hi>Importune,</hi> and perſecute us with the moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Imputations they can invent, and then with Fire and Faggot. But that they may ſeem to give ſome Anſwer to thoſe plain Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Reaſons that ſhine in their Eyes, they ſoar aloft, quite out of ſight, with Metaphyſicks, or ſo near out of ſight, that we can ſee nothing but a Cloud. The Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of One God, and One Perſon that is that One God, every Man and Woman can underſtand; that is, they know perfectly that One Perſon that is God, cannot be Two Perſons, each of which is God: and except they had been us'd from their Infancy, to ſay like Parrots, that Three Perſons are One God, and each One of them is that God, they would eaſily ſee the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of it. And indeed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People do worſhip God, far more agreeable to his Will, than the Learned; for theſe are obliged by the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, in worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping One God, to mind him as Three Perſons, that is, to have in their Mind the Idea of One Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty and only wiſe Perſon, who is One God by himſelf, and in the ſame Act to Adore two other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, each of which is as much God by himſelf, as the former. To wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Three that are equal one to another, and at the ſame time, and in the ſame Act to worſhip but One. But the Common People worſhip One only Almighty and moſt Merciful Father, through the Son
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64947:5"/>as Mediator, except they confound them with expreſs Mention of Two other Perſons; and then they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip expreſly Three Gods, as the Learned do always more ſubtilly. God Almighty, even the Father, knows, he has given us a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, That we ſhould worſhip him as One, the only Wiſe, the only Good, the only True, the only Holy, the only Potentate, and none other as God beſides him; which Commandment is as eaſy to be known by all the People that have Reaſon enough to underſtand Numbers, the difference between One and more than One, as it is neceſſary to be obſerved; but is impoſſible to be obſerved, becauſe impoſſible to be apprehended by the Common People, at leaſt, if the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſian</hi> Doctrine be true Divinity. <hi>Hear, O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>the Lord our God is One Lord:</hi> And, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all Thine Heart, with all thy Soul, and with all thy Might,</hi> (<hi>Deut.</hi> 6.4, 5.) But how ſhall we do to love each of Three Perſons that are equal, with all our Hearts? All the poor Labourers, with their Wives, in the Country, and all the Tankard-bearers of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> muſt go to School to Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> and he will teach them Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſicks and Mathematicks, and read a Lecture to them upon the Three Dimenſions, <hi>Long, Broad,</hi> and <hi>Tall,</hi> of <hi>One Cube:</hi> They muſt love God the Father, who is the Length of the Cube, with all their Hearts, and then God the Son, who is the Breadth, with all their Hearts too, and God the Holy Ghoſt in the ſame manner too.</p>
            <p>And if we meaſure this Cube with the Infallible Rule of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we find that this Long Cube [the Father] ſent this Broad Cube [the Son] on a Meſſage, as far as from Heaven to Earth, [<hi>John</hi> 6.38.] and anon after ſent this tall or deep Cube [the Holy Ghoſt] after him, [<hi>Matth.</hi> 3.16.] in the mean time he abode in Heaven himſelf. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, this broad Cube [the Son] is not commenſurable with this long Cube the Father, neither Northward nor Southward, in Knowledg (<hi>Mark</hi> 13.32.) or Power, (<hi>John</hi> 14.28.) In like manner this tall Cube [the Holy Ghoſt] receives of this long and broad Cube to make him taller and deeper, <hi>John</hi> 16.14.</p>
            <p>I fancy the poor People would apprehend it better by ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblance as this: Suppoſe one Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (<hi>Mary</hi>) to be married to Three Men at once, <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John; I,</hi> Mary, <hi>take thee</hi> Peter, James, <hi>and</hi> John <hi>to be my wedded Husband,</hi> &amp;c. Here are indeed Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but only One Husband; the Husbandhood is but One, though the Perſons are Three, each of which is Husband to <hi>Mary,</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> is obliged, by the Contract of Marriage, to pay Conjugal Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Duty to each of them. Methinks this is a more familiar pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel than that of a Cube. I do the rather make uſe of this Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, becauſe the Learned and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> in his Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Doctrine of the Bleſſed Trinity, tells us, <q>We muſt allow the Divine Perſons to be real ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Beings, <hi>Pag.</hi> 47.</q> And in <hi>Pag.</hi> 67. he ſaith, <q>The Father— feels himſelf to be the Father, and not the Son, nor the Holy Ghoſt: The Son in like manner feels himſelf to be the Son, and not the Father nor Holy Ghoſt; and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64947:5"/>ſo the Holy Ghoſt—As <hi>James</hi> feels himſelf to be <hi>James,</hi> and not <hi>Peter</hi> nor <hi>John,</hi> which proves them to be diſtinſt Perſons.</q> Thus Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> may ſee that his Notions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Trinity are old faſhion'd, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s are of the new Mode. But if he deſires to hare his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblances further diſplayed, I am told he may find them ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd in a Book, written in <hi>French,</hi> titled <hi>Le Nouveau Viſionaire</hi> againſt M. <hi>Jurieu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I did confeſs indeed that Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Explanation of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Perſons was far more clear and full than yours: But I had thought the Orthodox would not hare granted ſo much, and ſo it ſeems did you too. By this time we came near the end of your Letter; in which, he ſaid, there were ſtill the ſame Calumnies over and over. Only he took notice of one Text of Scripture you inſert, which you had not before, namely <hi>John</hi> 1.1, 14. <hi>The Word was God,</hi> and, <hi>The Word was made Fleſh.</hi> This (ſaith he) I confeſs were to the purpoſe; if by the term <hi>The Word</hi> could be meant nothing elſe but a Pre-exiſting Perſon, and by the term <hi>God</hi> nothing but God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty the Creator of Heaven and Earth, and if taking thoſe terms in thoſe Senſes did not make St. <hi>John</hi> write Nonſenſe; and if by Fleſh could be meant nothing but a Man, how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſoever, and not a Mortal Man, ſubject to Infirmities: But all theſe things are otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>For, 1. The Ancient Orthodox Senſe, at the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards for ſome Centuries, was this: In the beginning of the World, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all Worlds, the Son of God did exiſt, and that Son was with God his Father, and that Son was <hi>very God of very God,</hi> not numerically, but ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fically, as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> are of the ſame Subſtance. Now this Opinion was rejected by the Schoolmen, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing two Gods. And the Modern Orthodox underſtand it thus: <q>In the beginning before all Worlds, or from Eternity, the Son a diſtinct Perſon did exiſt, and that Son was with God his Father, and the Son was that God with whom he was.</q> But if they be tied to take the terms in the ſenſe of their Opinion, they muſt expound thus: <q>The Son <hi>was with God,</hi> that is, with the Father, himſelf and the Holy Ghoſt; and the Son was the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</q> Or, according to Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> the Breadth of the Cube, was with the Length, Breadth and Depth of the ſame Cube, and the Breadth was the Cube. And for the fourteenth Verſe, they ſay not, the Word or Son was made Fleſh, but, God the Son by the Holy Ghoſt coming upon the bleſſed Virgin, and the Power of the moſt High over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowing her, was united to a Human Body and Soul. The <hi>Arian</hi> Senſe you may ſee in a late Tract, entituled, <hi>A Vindication of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> That God firſt made a Super-Angelical Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, call'd the Son, and through that Son, and by the Holy Ghoſt, fram'd this World, and Man within it; This Being was with <hi>God,</hi> and was an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical <hi>God;</hi> and this Son, call'd <hi>The Word,</hi> became Incarnate. The <hi>Socinian</hi> Senſe was thus: In the beginning of the Goſpel (<hi>Mark</hi> 1.1.) was Jeſus called the Word, becauſe he was the prime and chief Expounder and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel; and this Word was with God, aſcended into Heaven, (<hi>John</hi> 3.13.) and deſcended thence, and being anointed with the Holy Ghoſt and Power, being thus ſanctified, and ſew into the World, was far more
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64947:6"/>deſervedly called the Son of God, and God, then thoſe among the Jews to whom the Word of God came, who yet were called Gods, (<hi>John</hi> 10.35, 36.) or than that Angel who appeared to <hi>Manoch,</hi> (<hi>Judg.</hi> 13.22.) And the Evangeliſt having ſaid in <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. that this true Light, as well as Word, or Light-Bringer, gave Power to thoſe that believed in him to be the Sons of God, he ſays in <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14. that He, the Word, was himſelf, as well as they, a Mortal and Frail Man.</p>
            <p>The Senſe of <hi>Paul</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch An.</hi> 262. (as I have read ſomewhere in <hi>Melancthon</hi>) and the Senſe of ſome in our Days was, That this term <hi>Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> muſt be taken for the beginning of the World, and the term <hi>The Word,</hi> being the Subject of the Hiſtory in the very Front of it, muſt be taken pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, and by way of eminence, for the Goſpel Word. But a Word, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> being twofold, Internal in the Mind, and External in the Speech, the Word here ſpoken of, muſt mean the Internal Word of God by way of excellence, that is, the Goſpel Decree, as it is taken alſo in <hi>Titus</hi> 1.3. where the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> having mentioned the Truth which is after Godlineſs, in hope of Eternal Life, goes on and ſays, <hi>which God, that cannot lye, promiſed</hi> [decreed to promiſe, or in purpoſe promiſed] <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World began:</hi> hath in due time manifeſted <hi>his Word</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] through preaching. This Word was with or in God, not yet manifeſted: and the <hi>Word was God;</hi> here God being the Predicate, muſt have ſuch a Senſe as can agree to the Subject <hi>Word,</hi> either moſt Divine, as <hi>Spirit</hi> for <hi>Spiritual, John</hi> 6.63. and the very term <hi>God, Gal.</hi> 1.10. for the Doctrine of the Goſpel, and in the 18th Verſe of this Chapter, <hi>John</hi> 1. in the ſame Senſe; or as <hi>Grotius</hi> would have it, for the Word of God: but die former Senſe ſeems far better: All things were made by it, to wit, as a Rule or chief Deſign. According to this Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the <hi>Word</hi> muſt not be taken for a Perſon in the firſt five Verſes, nor till the Evangeliſt had ſaid in the ſixth and ſeventh Verſes, That the Baptiſt being a Man ſent of God, was not the Light which was in the Word men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, that is, was not the Bringer or Preacher of the Light; for that muſt be the Senſe, when a Man is ſaid to be, or not to be the Light. But that which is denied of <hi>John,</hi> is affirmed of another, to whom he bare Witneſs, and that was Jeſus, as appears afterwards. He was the true Light, that is, Light-Bringer, which coming into the World, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightneth every Man. And now having laid a ſufficient Ground for taking the <hi>Light,</hi> in an improper Senſe, for Light-Bringer, his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cannot eaſily be miſtaken, when in the fourteenth Verſe, he calls the ſame Man <hi>The Word,</hi> that is, the perſonal Word, or Great Goſpel-Prophet, and ſays, That <hi>The Word</hi> was, was made, or was born Fleſh; that is, a Frail and Mortal Man, (not barely a Man) for ſo the Word <hi>Fleſh</hi> does always ſignify when it's applied to Man; and Chriſt is now a Man, but not Fleſh. <hi>The Word wets made Fleſh,</hi> does not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that this great Word, Prophet, or Meſſenger of that Word, did exiſt before he was born, no more than that Phraſe in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45. <hi>The firſt Man</hi> Adam <hi>was made a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Soul,</hi> proves or implies that <hi>Adam</hi> did pre-exiſt before he was made a living Soul.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64947:6"/>
            <p>Here, Sir, I interpoſed, and told my Gentleman, That this Expoſition ſeem'd very uncouth and ſtrange; I had never heard of it before, and therefore it was not eaſy for me to apprehend it, much more to receive it. He readily conſented to what I ſaid; and added, That it's a thing which makes Unitarian Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſeem forc'd and unnatural, namely, becauſe we have imbib'd from our Youth, and even from our Catechiſms, contrary Expoſitions: But if they were both propos'd to one that had never heard of either of 'em before, he was perſwaded the Trinitarian Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions would ſeem far more harſh and forc'd, nay, contradictious and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd. For, to inſtance in this very Text of <hi>John,</hi> what un-prejudiced Man could ever imagine that this Text ſhould be the Ground of the Doctrine of Two Perſons in God, when nothing is more clear in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Reaſon, than the Unity of God, which neceſſarily implies the Unity of his Perſon. I have been the larger in ſetting out this Expoſition (ſaith he) becauſe I knew it would be difficult for you to apprehend it.</p>
            <p>There is yet another Expoſition of this Scripture, which is derived from the Great <hi>Grotius,</hi> and may be found in the <hi>Brief Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> which I ſpoke of. But I think I have ſaid enough to convince any Man that is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly prejudic'd, that this is an obſcure Scripture: For as every one of theſe Senſes finds ſome ſpecious Grounds in the Text, ſo never a one of them can clearly anſwer all the Objections that are levied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and that of the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians</hi> leaſt of all: Therefore your Doctor writes, either unlike a Divine, or like a Cenſorious, I will not ſay Malicious Perſon; when he ſays, If God ſay, <hi>The Word was God,</hi> and <hi>The Word was made Fleſh;</hi> ſhall we ſay, not ſo, only becauſe we cannot tell How? As if theſe Sayings were ſo clear, that they admitted no Senſe but his, which underſtands by <hi>The Word</hi> an Eternally pre-exiſting Perſon, whereas the term <hi>Ho Logos</hi> in Greek, which we tranſlate <hi>The Word,</hi> Speech, or Saying, is found (I ſuppoſe) forty times in the New Teſtament taken im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſonally for the Goſpel, or ſome Speech: It's Three and twenty times ſo uſed in this One Evangeliſt of St. <hi>John,</hi> and for the moſt part oppos'd to the Perſon of Chriſt; and on the other hand, there is not one Text, except this in 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.14. where it can rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably ſignify a Perſon, except we reckon that in 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. for one, which I have ſhew'd to be uncertain, and not to have the Authority of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sacred Scripture. As for that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13.—<hi>his Name is called, The Word of God,</hi> that is, not the ſame with <hi>The Word</hi> ſimply; and though it denote a Perſon, yet it's one whoſe Veſture was dipt in Blood, which ſhews him to be <hi>a Man,</hi> a glorious Captain. Let all rational Men judge, Whether it's more reaſonable to take a term in ſuch Senſe, as it's almoſt always to be found in in the ſame Divine Author, than in the Senſe of <hi>Philo</hi> a Jew, or <hi>Plato</hi> a Heathen. So that the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> have far the moſt reaſon to cry out of forc'd Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations, whereby to deprive God of an incommunicable Attribute, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his Unity: And they defend theſe Interpretations with ſuch Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, as are either not intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, or which infer abſurd Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64947:7"/>Such are the Diſtinctions between the Eſſence and the Divine Perſons; of the threefold manner of Exiſtence of God; of Circuminceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or the mutual Penetration or mutual Inexiſtence of the Divine Perſons among themſelves; of God taken perſonally and eſſentially in Scripture; of the Name <hi>Father</hi> ſometimes ſignifying the Father a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, ſometimes the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; of the Eternal Generation, or God's Eternal beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Son equal to himſelf, and yet not another God; of the Divine Operations within and without the Eſſence, whence it is that the Internal are attributed to the Perſons diſtinctly, the External to them all Three, though One only be named; of the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or God the Son not being made a Man, but joyning himſelf to a Man in an Hypoſtatical Union; hence of two Natures in One Perſon, of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of Properties, whereby that which is ſpoken of Chriſt's Divine Nature, is understood to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to him according to his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, and <hi>vice verſâ:</hi> and many more confounding Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they uſe, without which the Holy Scriptures cannot be underſtood in the Senſe of <hi>Trinitarians:</hi> but I am weary with reciting them. Here he broke off, and I roſe to take my leave of him. I told him, as the truth is, That I had long taken the Doctrine of the Trinity for granted, and began but now to inquire into it, therefore could not readily reply to thoſe things he had urged, who, I perceived, was well vers'd in the Point; but I would, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſider it. He thank'd me much for my Friendly Viſit and Patience in hearing him, and hop'd to ſee me again ſhortly upon this Occaſion.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, give me leave to tell you, that though I was much ſatisfied with your Letter, taking it for granted you had given a true Repreſentation of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> yet finding by this Diſcourſe, it is far otherwiſe with them, that they have as high a Veneration for the Holy Scripture as we, that they uſe their Reaſon no more than reaſonable Men ought to do, <hi>viz.</hi> for the find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the true Senſe of Scripture; that they reject the Doctrine of the Trinity, not only becauſe it's contrary to Reaſon, but more eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it's contrary to moſt plain and clear Scriptures, as they conceive; that they have no need of thoſe nice Diſtinctions that we are forc'd to make uſe of; that the Texts you alledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them as moſt clear, are not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding very doubtful and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure. For theſe Reaſons, and others of this Kind, I am more diſſatisfied in this Matter than I was at firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I perceive by your Letter, that nothing convincing can be urged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, even by them that are moſt Learned, ſuch as you are. If you can and will pleaſe to take upon you the trouble of another Letter, to anſwer theſe my Scruples and Doubts, you will add thereby much more ſtrength to the many Obligations wherein you have already bound,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SIR, Your much obliged—</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64947:7"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Had no ſooner finiſh'd my Letter, but you were pleaſed to ſend me another, which is an Anſwer to a Letter you received from an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Gentleman, propoſing ſome Objections againſt your former Letter. My Gentleman hearing of it, came to give me a Viſit, and when he had read this your ſecond Letter, he made his Exceptions to two or three Paſſages in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You ſay, <hi>By Perſonality, I mean that Diſtinction (whatever it be) whereby the Three are diſtinguiſhed; but what that is, I do not pretend to determine. And if I ſhould gueſs, for it will be but gueſſing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now (ſaith he) our Saviour in the Holy Scripture tells us plainly, <hi>This is Life Eternal, that they might know thee</hi> (Father) <hi>the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent,</hi> John 17.3. Do not theſe Names and Characters diſtinguiſh the one from the other? Does any thing diſtinguiſh Two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons more fully, than that the one is Father to the other, and the other his Son? The one prayeth, the other is prayed unto. The one is not only God, but the only true God; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is he whom the Father, the only true God hath ſent: and he that is ſent by him is Jeſus, the Name of that Man who was the Son of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> and the Name <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſignifies, that he was anointed with the Holy Ghoſt and Power, for the performance of that Office of ſaving Men from their Sins, whereunto he was ſent by the only true God his Father. I challenge the Learned Doctor, and the Learnedeſt Doctor at <hi>Oxford,</hi> (if there be any more Learned than he) to ſhew me a clearer or plainer Diſtinction between God and <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi>'s not pretending to determine the Diſtinction between God the Sender, and Jeſus Chriſt the Sent, but calling that Determination <hi>Gueſſing,</hi> is in effect to deny the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Chriſt's Words, and to call his clear and full determination of that which we are to know for obtaining the Eternal Life, <hi>Gueſſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his next Paragraph, ſpeaking of the ſame Matter, he Complements ſome Body, <hi>craving leave to be ignorant of what the Scripture doth not tell him.</hi> Now if I did not conſider the vaſt power Prejudice and long Prepoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion have over Mens Minds, I ſhould determine the Doctor to be wilfully blind: But it's plain, he bears falſe. Witneſs againſt our Lord, and the Holy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64947:8"/>Scripture, whilſt he ſays the Scripture doth not tell him, what it plainly tells him and every Woman that can but read it.</p>
            <p>The following Paragraph is <hi>Of the damnatory SENTENCES</hi> in the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, <hi>which ſeem,</hi> ſay you, <hi>to be annexed only to ſome Generals, which the Author thought necessary,</hi> as the Trinity and Incarnation of Chriſt. To which he excepted thus: This Creed being made (as it ſeems to the Learned) many hundreds of Years after the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed, which contains all General Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, and two or three hundred Years after the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, which explains the Doctrine of the Trinity and the Incarnation more particularly, the Author of it was very impertinent, if he did not deſign all his Explication to be believed upon pain of Damnation. But if that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument were wanting, who can read the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, and find <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> in the beginning, middle, and concluſion, and can then have the face to deny, that the not believing of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Clauſe is damnable? I am ſorry to find ſo much Daubing in Dr. <hi>Wallis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then we came to your further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining the parallel of the Cube; where you ſay, it may be ſaid of it, that, <hi>This long Things is a Cube, and ſo, This which is broad, or this which is high is a Cube.</hi> But the (ſaith he) he that ſays, This long Thing is a Cube, doth in ſo ſaying, ſay, This long Thing is broad and high: conſequently in Parallel each Perſon is Three Perſons.</p>
            <p>This is all he took notice of at that time, for he was in haſte. And I having conſidered what he had ſaid before, and finding ſo much Reaſon and Suita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs to Scripture in it, could not tell how to defend theſe Paſſages, and therefore remit them to you, hoping you will honour with a Return,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>SIR, Your</hi>—</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64947:8"/>
            <head>Whether Trinity or Unity more dangerous?</head>
            <p>THE Trinitarians and Unitarians agree that there is but one God moſt High: they both agree that the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is that God moſt High. They dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in this, that Jeſus before he was a Man and from Eternity, and alſo the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, as diſtinct Perſons from God the Father, were and are each of them as perfectly God moſt High as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo that each of them is Almighty, Eternal, All-knowing, only Wiſe, only Good, Infinite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> equal to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Trinitarians aſſert theſe things, the Unitarians deny them.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion hereupon is, Which of theſe Parties are in the moſt dangerous Error, ſuppoſing them to be in Error, now the one, now the other?</p>
            <p>If the Trinitarians err, they worſhip two Perſons in God equal to one that is undoubtedly God, that is, they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip three Almighty and only Wiſe Perſons, which are not diſtinguiſhable from three moſt High Gods.</p>
            <p>If the Unitarians err, they avoid that Error of worſhipping three Perſons which they cannot diſtinguiſh from three Gods; but their Error lies in holding ſo ſtrictly to the Oneneſs of God, as well in Perſon as Eſſence, that they do not acknowledg, beſides that One, two more Perſons to be equally God, as well as that One, whom both Parties agree to be ſo: that is, they err in not acknowledging two unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Perſons in God, but holding that the God and Father of Chriſt is God alone, only neceſſary and all-ſufficient.</p>
            <p>If the Trinitarians err, they err againſt the common Reaſon of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and moſt plain and expreſs Scriptures, which aſſert that God is One, or that there is but one Supream God, and always ſpeak of him as one only Perſon. If the Unitarians err, they err againſt the doubtful Senſe of ſome obſcure Texts, which more fairly admit of another Interpretation conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the Unity of the Perſon of God.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, the Queſtion is, Whether the Term <hi>God</hi> includes only one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or three Perſons? one Almighty Perſon, or three diſtinct Almighty Perſons? And whether the former or the latter is the more dangerous Error, which ſoever is found an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
